Monad 变压器不是最漂亮的东西，他们没有井
Monad transformers are not the prettiest thing they don't have a well
建立理论和数学就像是解决这个问题的一种方法。
founded theory and math are just like a way to get through this problem.
我们将研究具有良好理论基础的自由 monad。
And we're gonna look at free monads which do have a well founded theory.
但这是一个组合，
But this is one compose,
我只是想证明函子可以组合，但 monad 不能。
I just wanted to show that functors compose, but monads do not.
所以让我们在这里跳到变压器。
So let's jump into transformers here.
好的，
All right,
让我们进入一种情况，其中有一个变压器会很有用。
let's get into a situation where it would be useful to have a transformer.
[笑] 所以让我们继续说，我们有一个应用程序，
[LAUGH] So let's go ahead and say, we have an app,
这个应用程序会非常酷。
and this app is gonna be super cool.
与我们之前所做的非常相似，我们有这些嵌套类型
Very similar to what we were doing before, we have these nested types
在其他类型中，我们因此遇到了这些问题。
inside other types and we run into these problems because of that.
所以每当我试图找到一些东西时，我都会有一个任务和一个要么
So I have a task and an Either whenever I try to find something,
它会尝试在表中找到一些东西，因为我的查询会放它
it's gonna try to find something in the table given my query is gonna put it
或者说我可能没有找到它，我们要把它放在一个任务中。
in an either saying I might not have found it, we're gonna put that in a task.
因为我们正在尝试对数据库类型的交互进行建模。
Because we're trying to model a database kind of interaction.
所以我们在这里要做的是说我要
So what we'll do here is say I'm going to
找到 ID 为 1 的用户，这就是我。
find the users where ID is 1, so that's me.
好的，马克在这儿。
All right, Mark's over here.
看起来我在关注
And it looks like I'm following
那边的这个人，我在跟踪马克，而马克也在跟踪我。
this person over there, and I'm following Mark, and Mark's following me.
很酷，所以我们要做的就是让我们映射一下。
Cool, so what we're gonna try to do is all right let's map over this.
我想做的是找到我的追随者。
What I wanna do is find my follower.
所以它实际上是一个链条，因为我们要做另一个发现，对吧？
So it's actually a chain because we're gonna do another find, right?
给自己留点空间。
Give myself some room.
好的，所以我们得到了这个，无论是用户，对吧？
All right, so we get this, Either user, right?
并且与铁杆功能类中的任一个用户，
And with the Either user in the hardcore functional class,
无论你在做什么都是在运行自然转换
whatever you're doing was running natural transformations to
把两者都变成一项任务，这样我们就可以在每次进行的时候把它们弄下来。
turn the Either into a task so we can kind of crunch them down each time as we go.
在这里，我们将采取不同的方法。
Here we're gonna take a different approach.
我们要制作这种怪物，这个任务要么使用 monad 转换器。
We're gonna make this kind of monstrosity, this task Either using monad transformers.
但让我进一步说明我们为什么要这样做。
But let me demonstrate a little bit further on why we wanna do this.
因为我有一个Either 用户，所以我不能，我没有用户。
So because I have an Either user, I can't, I don't have a user.
因为我正在调用链，所以我必须返回另一个任务，对吗？
And because I'm calling chain, I have to return another task, right?
这是一项任务，用户和
This is a task and Either the user and
如果我要链接，我必须返回另一个任务。
if I'm gonna chain that I have to return another task.
所以我要做的就是折叠我什至不知道如何做任务得到
So what I'll do is fold out the Either I don't even know how to do tasks get
在这里被拒绝，我猜。
rejected here, I guess.
然后在这里，我们有一个用户，
And then over here, we've got a user,
好的，现在我们想从下表中找到，
okay, now we wanna find from the following table,
其中 user_id 是我的 u.id，好吗？
where the user_id is my u.id, okay?
好吧，所以找，其实我觉得是follow_id是我的用户id，
All right, so find, actually I think it is follow_id is my user id,
follow_id，无所谓。
follow_id, doesn't really matter.
这只是为了证明我想得到这个正确的。
This is just just to demonstrate I wanna get this correct.
我们会找到错误的追随者。
We're gonna find the wrong followers.
好吧，太酷了。
All right, so cool.
但是现在我们有另一个用户，对吧？
But now we have another Either user, right?
这是一个痛苦的屁股，我们不断遇到这些Either用户。
It's a pain in the butt, we keep running into these Either users.
现在我们必须折叠它。
And now we have to fold that.
[笑]好吧，另一个在这里被拒绝，然后
[LAUGH] All right another rejected here, and then
现在我们有喜欢的追随者。
now we have our like following.
让我们暂时称之为 fo，我想从用户表中找到，
Let's call it fo for now, and I wanna find from the users table,
具有来自以下用户 ID 的 ID 的实际用户。
the actual user with ID that comes from the followings user ID.
好的，你看到这里发生了什么，我正在尝试使用此链接表来查找谁
Okay, you see what's happening here, I'm trying to use this link table to find who
是我的追随者，然后返回用户表以找到该用户。
are my followers and then go back to the user table to find that user.
这只是一场灾难 我只是不断地遇到这些任务
And it's just a disaster I just keep running into these tasks Either and
他们必须不断地折叠它们。
they have to keep folding them out.
让我们看看我们得到的答案。
Let's see what we get as an answer.
所以我要做的是 fork 那个错误，console.log。
So what I'm gonna do is fork that error, console.log.
因为我在这里找到了一个发现。
And because I ended on a find here.
[笑] 或者我可以换一个，对吧？
[LAUGH] Or I can another Either, right?
所以你再次得到一个Either用户，再一次
So you get a Either user again, once again and
那么就在这里，我们将把用户折叠到一个 console.error 或 console.log。
then right here we'll fold out either user to a console.error, or console.log.
让我们打电话。
And let's call up.
我们必须分叉它等待我们在那里分叉那很好。
And we have to fork it wait we fork it there that's fine.
只需在那里分叉，称之为应用程序。
Just fork it there call it app.
通常你想在外面叉，但是
Normally you want to fork outside but
无论如何，清除变形金刚/1。
whatever, c lear Transformers/1.
很酷，我们找到了 Mark，所以我们给了它我的 ID，然后我们找到了关注者 ID。
Cool we found Mark so we gave it my ID, and then we found the follower ID.
然后我们从用户中找到了以下用户 ID 和
And then we found from the users that user ID from the following and
然后我们得到马克，很酷。
then we get Mark, cool.
那么我们如何用 monad 变压器来解决这个问题呢？
So how do we solve this with monad transformers?
每个人都明白这个问题吗，比如这有多糟糕。
Does everybody understand the problem, like how much this sucks.
[笑]好吧，这很糟糕的原因。
[LAUGH] All right, the reason why this sucks.
[笑] 所以
[LAUGH] So
我们能做的就是说，好吧，我要制作一个名为 TaskEither 的新东西。
what we can do is is say, all right, I'm gonna make a new thing called TaskEither.
所以我会说任务转换器，我们要给它喂食，或者叫它 TaskEither。
So I'll say task transformer and we're gonna feed it either call that TaskEither.
好的，这样做是任务转换器创建了一个新任务
All right, what that did is task transformer created a new task much
像 compose 一样，创建了一个知道如何映射的新类型。
like compose, created a new type that knew how to map.
这东西知道怎么换链。
This thing knows how to change chain.
[笑] 但它是特定于每个 monad 的。
[LAUGH] But it's specific to each monad.
所以每个 monad 都应该有，有一个 elseT 和一个 IdT 等等。
So each monad should have, there's an EitherT, and an IdT and so on.
所以因为每个 monad 只能知道如何
So because each monad can only know how to
处理一些它自己的效果，然后在它里面的任何东西上调用chain。
deal with some its own effects, and then just call chain on whatever it has inside.
在这一点上它是通用的，但在这里是特定的。
It's like generic to this point, but it's specific here.
如果我想有趣地恢复任务，我现在可以给一个Id，现在我有任务了，
If I wanna recover task interestingly I can just give an Id now I have tasks back,
只是有点整洁。
just kinda neat.
这是一个美丽的财产，通过。
That's a little bit of a beautiful property that carries through.
所以你可以只定义变压器和
So you can define just the transformer and
只需将其应用于恒等函子即可恢复原始类型。
recover the original type just by applying it to the identity functor.
但我们在这里感兴趣的是 TaskT(Either)。
But what we're interested here is TaskT(Either).
那么我该如何处理这件事呢？
So how do I work with this thing?
让我告诉你它解决了什么问题。
Let me show you what problem it solves.
然后我们将在这里深入研究变压器的 API。
And then we'll kinda dig in play with the API of transformers here.
所以我们要说 TaskEither，这是一个问题。
So we're gonna say TaskEither, and here's something that's a problem.
任务要么接受，如果我说，
TaskEither will take, if I say of,
的 on TaskEither 会给我一个任务，要么有一个 x，对吧？
of on TaskEither will give me a task of an either have an x, right?
任务要么，我在这里有一个要么给我
Task either, and I have an Either here so that would give me
一个 TaskEither(Either(x)，他们会看到这就是 up 的作用。
a TaskEither(Either(x), they'll see that that's what up does.
它现在在两种类型中都放置了一个值，而我正在尝试放置一个它们不是。
It puts a value in both types now and I'm trying to put a Either they're not.
所以我要尝试做的事情，而不是我要做的事情叫做提升。
So what I'm gonna try to do, what I'm gonna do instead is called lift.
我想把我的要么提升到 TaskEither 中，所以
I wanna lift my Either into the TaskEither, so
它就像 of，但它不会复制那个内部类型。
it's just like of, but it won't duplicate that inner type.
大家看到了吗？
Does everybody see that?
So of 会给我Either(Either (x))。
So of would have given me Either(Either (x).
但是提升只是把它放在一个层次上
But lift just puts it one level in so
这是我们稍后将再次讨论的内容。
that's something that we're gonna look at in a minute again.
但那是一回事。
But that is a thing.
所以现在，如果我运行这个和生命编码的幽灵
So now, if I run this and the ghost of life coding
真好，我们可以说，好吧，现在我
is kind, we will be able to say, all right, well now I
不要获得任何用户，因为它知道如何正确链接这两种类型。
don't get an Either user because it knows how to chain correctly over both types.
所以我只会得到一个用户，这有多好？
So I'll just get a user, how nice is that?
现在我们可以找到东西，对吧？
Now we could just find stuff, right?
再说一次，如果我链接它，我只会得到另一个用户，对吗？
And again, if I chain that, I just get a another user, right?
好吧，我想这已经结束了，佛。
Well, I guess this is up, fo.
但是，是的，这里发生了什么，现在我有一个任务（要么）和
But yeah, so what's happened here, is now I had a Task(Either) and
我已经改变了它，所以我仍然有任务（或者（用户））。
I've changed it so I still have Task(Either(User)).
再一次，我已经链接了它，并且我得到了一个 Task(Either(User))。
And again, I've chained that, and I get a Task(Either(User)).
最后，我们 .fork 任务，我们还没有任务中的任一个用户，
And finally, we .fork the task, we still haven't Either user inside the task,
一个重要的区别是任务要么知道如何链接。
that's an important distinction is that task either knows how to chain.
但归根结底，这仍然是一项任务。
But at the end of the day, it's still a task holding an either.
因此，当我 fork 任务时，我会得到两者之一，而不仅仅是将用户给我。
So when I fork the task, I get the Either, it's not just gonna give me the user out.
它只是定义了那个东西的链。
It just defines chain on that thing.
所以现在如果我们运行它。
So now if we run it.
好吧，效果很好。
All right, it works great.
[笑] 将此更改为用户 ID，我们将得到
[LAUGH] For change this to user id, we'll get
另一个用户退出，是的，让我退出，很酷。
a different user out, yeah let me back out, cool.
所以关于 monad 转换器的问题，我们会多谈一点，但是
So questions on monad transformers, we are gonna talk a little bit more about it but
我只是不想留下这个例子来说明它正在解决什么问题，
I just don't wanna leave this example of what it's solving for,
然后我们将更多地了解它们的机制。
and then we'll play around with more about the mechanics of them.